<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of blazing starres in generall As well supernaturall as naturall: to what countries or people soeuer they appeare in the spacious world.</title>
            <title>Super huis anni post Christum natum M.D.XXXI. &amp; quolibet alio cometa exploratio. English</title>
            <author>Nausea, Friedrich, d. 1552.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72929</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18413.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123128</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898838</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152090</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72929)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2011:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of blazing starres in generall As well supernaturall as naturall: to what countries or people soeuer they appeare in the spacious world.</title>
                  <title>Super huis anni post Christum natum M.D.XXXI. &amp; quolibet alio cometa exploratio. English</title>
                  <author>Nausea, Friedrich, d. 1552.</author>
                  <author>Fleming, Abraham, 1552?-1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>imprinted by Bernard Alsop, and are to be sold by Edward Wright at his shoppe neere Christ Church Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Alexander Fleming, of: Nausea, Friedrich.  Super huis anni post Christum natum M.D.XXXI. &amp; quolibet alio cometa exploratio.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]²  B-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A treatise in generall of blazing starres.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with "sold by Henry Bell" in imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Comets --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF BLAZING <hi>STARRES IN Generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As well ſupernaturall as naturall: To what Countries or people ſoeuer they appeare in the ſpacious World.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>shooting star</figDesc>
               <p>SOVTH.</p>
               <p>WEST.</p>
               <p>NORTH.</p>
               <p>EAST.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Bernard Alſop,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Edward Wright</hi> at his ſhoppe neere Chriſt Church gate. 1618:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:2"/>
            <head>A Prognoſtication of Blazing Starres, according to the opinion of the Poet <hi>Pontanus.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>OF ſtirring winds, with bluſtering blaſts which blow,</l>
               <l>Of bloody broyles, by force in fatall fight:</l>
               <l>Of peoples pompe, the pitious ouerthrow.</l>
               <l>Of Potentates the death, in wofull plight:</l>
               <l>The Blazing Starres aloft like lampes of light</l>
               <l>In th'Eſt or Weſt of azure coloured skies,</l>
               <l>Forewarnings and ſignes when they ariſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ſtill they ſtand, and offer not to change</l>
               <l>The place, where firſt in ſight they caſt their beames,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall inſue much miſchiefe rare and ſtrange:</l>
               <l>As gaping wounds, and ſluzing bloody ſtreames,</l>
               <l>In foughten field, twixt nigh adioyning Realmes.</l>
               <l>Such ciuill ſtormes ſhall ouerrunne the land,</l>
               <l>That ſome ſhall bath in kindreds blood their hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if they take their courſe vnto the Eaſt,</l>
               <l>A ſigne it is that forreigne foes with force</l>
               <l>Prepare apace, to ſpoyle both moſt and leaſt:</l>
               <l>With edge of ſword ſweet life ſtill to diuorce</l>
               <l>From panting heart, deuoyde of all remorſe.</l>
               <l>Thus Eaſt or Weſt in ſight, they haue their dome,</l>
               <l>And ſignes they are of things in time to come.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:3"/>
            <head>Why, and whereupon Blazing Starres haue theyr Names, CHAP. I.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orſomuch as a man furniſhed with all kind of knowledge and learning, ſhould ſo ſearch after the vnderſtanding of great and high matters,<note place="margin">A reaſon for vnderſtanding of blazing ſtars.</note> that he haue not meaner things in contempt and diſdaine, by whoſe benefite (as experience teacheth) the greater are attained, becauſe they miniſter certain helps and aides to aſpire and reach vnto them. Hereupon it followeth, that leſſer things are not to bee neglected, without the which there is no paſſage to the greater, nor any poſſibilitie to pearce to the perfect proofe of them, except by the forerunning of them preparation be made for vs to aſcend. and climbe vp to the hidden knowledge of the other. Therefore, leſt this our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour lent and layde out for common vtility and profite ſhould be ſubiect to the biting blowes of furious enuie, and leſt ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire perfection in profeſſion, as alſo certainety in deliuering Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſhould complaine, that wee ſell ſhadowes for ſubſtances, phantaſies for verities, and imaginations for demonſtrations: we will ſay ſomewhat in the entrance of this worke, touching the name of a <hi>Comete</hi> or <hi>Blazing ſtarre,</hi> and ſo paſſe orderly to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The ſtarre which the Grecians call <hi>Cometa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Blazing ſtar is named after the forme and figure which it beareth.</note> the Latines <hi>Stella crinita,</hi> we Engliſhmen a <hi>Blazing ſttarre,</hi> hath his deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination (as well by the aſſertion of the one, as the other from the form and figure which it beareth, at ſuch time as it appeareth in the ayre: becauſe this kind of ſtarre ſeemeth (in our opinion and iudgement) to ſhoote out long ſtrakes of fire in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, or bright and lightſom ſparckles continued in length like
<pb facs="tcp:152090:4"/>
vnto the hayre, which the Grecians call <hi>Coma,</hi> and thereupon <hi>Cometa,</hi> and the <hi>Latines Crinis,</hi> whereof it is named <hi>Stella cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The names of Blazing ſtars.</note> ſo that the reſemblance or repreſentation which this Starre giueth, is the occaſion that it is called a <hi>Comet,</hi> or <hi>Blazing ſtar,</hi> As <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> called that ſtarre, which appeared at ſuch time as he publiſhed Pageants of pleaſure: and ſhewes of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, by the name of a Comete: and which <hi>Suetonius Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillus</hi> called <hi>Sidus crinitum,</hi> and diuers others haue ſemblably termed,</p>
            <p>Neyther was the Impoſition of this name abſurde, or againſt reaſon:<note place="margin">The likenes of blazing ſtars as ſomtimes they appeare.</note> for whoſoeuer ſhall iudiciouſly behold thoſe kinde of Starres, he ſhall perceyue, though not moſt perfectly, yet not very darkly) how it ſhooteth out long and ſlender lines of ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fire, this way and that way, inſomuch, as a man would thinke and ſuppoſe the ſame not much vnlike vnto ſcattred hayre to a broome or a rodde of Byrch, to the tayle of a Peacocke, to the bearde of a man, &amp;c. as we are taught by demonſtration.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>That Blazing Stars are ſundry and diuers. CHAP. II.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BLazing Starres</hi> are not onely very many in number, but alſo diuers in appearance. The Sect of the Stoykes ſayde, that they are beyond two and thirty,<note place="margin">The Stoyckes opinion of Blazing ſtars.</note> of whoſe ſundry names and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall effects, <hi>Abienus</hi> not vnwiſely hath written.</p>
            <p>Concerning their number and names, we are héere to be not curious: wherefore we will come to their colours and likeneſſes wherein there is not an vniformity and generall agréement, but a difference, For ſome <hi>blazing-Starres</hi> ſeeme bloud redde, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to behold,<note place="margin">Blazing ſtars differ in colour</note> and (as it were) criſped and curled in the Crowne or vpper part, tending towards the Skies: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they are commonly called Comets. of which the Poet hath this ſaying:
<q>
                  <l>Like as in moyſt and dewie night,</l>
                  <l>When Comets red as bloud,</l>
                  <l>Appeare aloft: the ſpectacle,</l>
                  <l>and ſigne is little good.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:4"/>This Figure haue they, when they are thicke on the one ſide, and ſtretched out in length on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>Some Blazing Starres there be,<note place="margin">Blazing ſtars vary in figure. Trailed ſtars.</note> which haue a certayne han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging downeward at their lower part, in the likeneſſe of a long beard, or the mawne of a horſe: which happeneth by reaſon of the thin matter and ſubſtance which is in the other parts, which kind of ſtars are called <hi>Pogonii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other ſome there are, which appeare in the likeneſſe of a ſpeare or Iauelin, and they are called <hi>Acontij:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Speare ſtars.</note> or ſuch a one as teſtifieth <hi>Plinie,</hi> did <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> in his Conſulſhip, penne paſſing and excellent Poems, or Verſes of notable inuention and ſingular conueyance.</p>
            <p>Other ſome there are, ſhorter ſomewhat then the former,<note place="margin">Sword ſtarres.</note> and they be ſhapt towards the top like a ſword, whereupon they are called <hi>Piphij,</hi> reſembling in colour gold after a ſort, but yet ſo not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, that (of all other) they are moſt pale, wanting beames, blazes, or ſtrakes: hauing neuertheleſſe a cereain bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them, like the glittering of a ſword.</p>
            <p>Other ſome there are which are called <hi>Phitites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tun ſtarres.</note> in forme and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion like a Tunne, hauing in the hollow part of them the ſhew of a ſmoaky and ſmothering flame, much like vnto the Blacke-Smiihs Forge, or veſſels daubed and ſméered with pitch, ſet on fire, which caſt a darke and miſtie light, and men haue ſometimes vſed for the preſeruing and freſh kéeping of their drinke.</p>
            <p>There are beſides them that we haue reckoned <hi>Comets</hi> called <hi>Certarij,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horne ſtarres.</note> becauſe they appeare to our ſight in the ſimilitude and likenes of a Horn: Such a one was ſéene, when the Grecians en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped at <hi>Salamina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Otherſome alſo there are, which be called <hi>Lampades,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lampe ſtars.</note> becauſe they caſt a ſhew of a burning torch, or flaming Lampe of which ſort ſundry haue béene, and that not very ſeldome.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, ſome there are which be called <hi>Hippci,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mawne ſtars.</note> becauſe they ſéeme to haue about them (as it were) a Horſe Mawne, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing round about them in circle wiſe, with ſtrange mouing and ſwifteneſſe.</p>
            <p>To bée ſhort, ſome Blazing Starres are ſéene in the Ayre, gliſtering with ſtrakes and ſtreames like bright ſiluer, that it paſſeth the ability of mans eye to looke and behold them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:152090:5"/>
(as in a cleare glaſſe) God is repreſented, in the likeneſſe and ſhape of a man. And ſuch a one (as ſome do hold opinion) was that which appeared to the Wiſemen in the Eaſt,<note place="margin">A Blazing ſtar reprpſenting as it were in a glaſſe, the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God.</note> and conducted them to the place where Chriſt was borne: concerning the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing whereof, thus ſayde he to the <hi>Hieroſolomite. Wee haue ſeene his ſtarre in the Eaſt, and are come to doe him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But touching this, we purpoſe (peraduenture) to ſay ſomwhat in the winding vp of this worke. We know not that beſides theſe which we haue rehearſed, there be many more formes and figures of <hi>Comets</hi> or <hi>blazing ſtarres,</hi> and many more ſorts, of which particularly to diſcourſe, is not our meaning or ontent, nor yet a matter of ſuch weight and importance, that it ſhould require preſent and perfect handling: we will therefore to that which is more neceſſary.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>In what part of Heauen blazing ſtarres appeare moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly. CHAP. III,</head>
            <p>THey that haue written things notable, and profitable of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, and haue diſcourſed things concerning the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and gouernments of Starres, in ſuch ſort and order, that the knowledge iſſuing from their trauels, offereth fruit not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing repentance:<note place="margin">In what part of heauen Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtars are ſeene.</note> They (I ſay) haue affirmed, that Blazing Starres neuer appeare in the Weſt part of Heauen: but either vnder the North, in ſome one part or other, but vncertaine: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, moſt commonly in that bright and cleare part, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Milkie Circle:</hi> or elſe (which is ſeldome ſéene come to paſſe) they appeare in the South Pole, but yet without any blazce, in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeaſons of Winter eſpecially: yet it is recorded, that a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me appeared to the <hi>Aethopians,</hi> and to the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and that the King of thoſe people, gaue that Blazing Starre a name, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it <hi>Typon,</hi> becauſe it had in it a double reſemblance, namely of a round ball, and of a fire, in ſo much, that according to the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſenſe, it might not ſo aptly be called a Comet or Blazing Starre, as a fiery or flaming ball, or a round compaſſed and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning knot.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:5"/>
            <head>At what time of the yeare blazing ſtarres appeare, and how long they continue. CHAP. IIII.</head>
            <p>ALthough <hi>Damaſcene</hi> (an Authour in my iudgement wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy reuerence (is of opinion that a Blazing ſtarre, is a ſtar newly made and created for the time preſent, which vaniſheth out of ſight, and ceaſeth to appeare, when the thing whereof it is a ſignification is accompliſhed, and come to paſſe: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, experience (whom writers name, the Miſtreſſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny myſteries) informeth and teacheth vs, that a Blazing Starre may appeare at any ſeaſon of the yeare: but more often in ſummer and then ſpecially, when the ſtarre called <hi>Canicula</hi> ariſeth, and ruleth the weather and time of the yeare, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the influence, and that they continue ſeuen dayes at the leaſt, and not aboue foureſcore at the moſt, the authoritie of <hi>Plinie,</hi> giuing countenance to this opinion.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, this aſſertion, together with the teſtimony of <hi>Plinie</hi> may be improued by examples: For (as it is vniuerſally knowne) a <hi>Comet,</hi> which appeared before the ouerthrow of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> was ſeene blazing in the Element, to the wonderfull aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the people, by the ſpace of a whole yeare, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Ioſephus</hi> verified.</p>
            <p>But we muſt note, that this Comet, and the appearance of the ſame, which was full of horror, is not to be aſcribed vnto Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but to be attributed immediatly vnto God,<note place="margin">The opinion of the Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goriſts touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Blazing ſtarres.</note> the Father and founder of Nature, although the ſect of the <hi>Pythagoriſts</hi> thought, that all Blazing ſtars were to be referred vnto Nature who hath prouided that their appearing ſhould be at certaine definite, and appointed times of the yeare.</p>
            <p>Touching theſe Blazing Stars alſo, of the ſame ſect there was ſome, who ſuppoſed they were perpetuall ſtars, and not tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and that they had an ordinary courſe to run, as other ſtarres haue their reuolution and circular motion, and that their appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring procéeded from none other cauſe, then when they were, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken and left of the Sun, whoſe brightnes and néereneſſe is the occaſion as they thinke, that Blazing ſtars do not appeare.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:6"/>
            <head>Whereof Blazing ſtarres are engendered (according to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Diuines) and what they are indeede. CHAP. V.</head>
            <p>THe Religious Diuines, like very well of this plauſible and true opinion, that <hi>Blazing ſtarres</hi> come of no other cauſe, then from the holy Counſell and Prouidence of God; that there is no matter of their generation,<note place="margin">Originall of Blazing ſtars.</note> as Phyloſophers imagine, but that God maketh them immediate meſſengers and Miniſters of his will, according to the time and place, as it beſt pleaſeth his hie and eternall Maieſtie: (that by them) he might giue vs aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of afterclaps, to prepare our ſelues onward to méete his fatherly mercy, or to ſuffer the bitternes of his ſharpe iudgement. Wherevpon they inferre this conſequent, that <hi>Blazing Stars</hi> are ſupernaturall, and méere worlds wonder.</p>
            <p>To whoſe Sentence I agree, and moſt willingly aſſent, being thereto moued by arguments of forcible perſwaſion, and in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber infinite. Principally, becauſe it is a Chriſtians duety, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe more to Gods prouidence, then to the force of Nature, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath not onely Created, but alſo doth diſpoſe and gouerne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Some Blazing ſtarres natural, otherſome ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall.</note>Yet for all that, I may not vtterly deny, that they are natural, for ſo much as I am not (or at leaſt ought not to be) ignorant, that Nature cauſeth <hi>blazing ſtarres;</hi> howbeit ſo, that God is the Originall and principall worker of ſuch wonders and that their ground and cauſes are naturall, and not ſo ſecret and doubtfull: but that otherwhile the capacity and reaſon of man may conceiue and compaſſe them. And yet contrarywiſe, I ſtand not in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that thoſe <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> are ſupernaturall, which the moſt mightie Monarch of the heauens, Creator of all creatures, and Maker of all Starres and Spirits, raiſeth of nothing to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, vpon a ſudden, in a moment and pricke of time, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of all men, and to the reueal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of his Omnipotency.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All things are poſsible to God.</note>Expedient and neceſſary it is to beleeue, that with God all things are in ability, and that whatſoeuer is done eyther by day, or by night, naturally or ſupernaturally, it commeth to paſſe by his appointment, and that it pleaſeth him otherwhiles to create ſomething of ſomething, and otherwiles againe, ſomething of
<pb facs="tcp:152090:6"/>
nothing. To that which neuer had matter, can he giue faſhion and figure, and beautifie that with forme and comelines, which neuer had Foundation nor beeing. It conſiſteth in his might to moyſten the earth with ſhowres diſtilling from the cleare skies, without the meanes of lowring and dropping cloudes. He can worke both wayes, to whom nothing is impoſſible: Now gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the cloudes together in an heape, from the vttermoſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and coaſts of the world, now turning againe lightning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to raine, which couering the heauens with cloudes, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring raine for the land: For, <hi>Great is the Lord, mighty is his power, and of his wiſdome there is no number or end:</hi> And therefore I am eaſily drawne to belieue, that <hi>Blazing Starres</hi> may immediately appeare from God, and be ſupernatural, when it pleaſeth God, vpon (ſome ſingular cauſe) to giue them begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, matter, and ſubſtance of nothing.</p>
            <p>Such a Blazing Starre (no doubt) was that Piller of the cloude,<note place="margin">The piller of the cloud, and the plller of fire were Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtars ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall. The Blazing ſtarre which appeared in Ieruſalem, was ſupernaturall.</note> whereby the Lord (in olde time) moſt miraculouſly went before the Iſraelites his people out of the Aegyptian Soile into the Land of Promiſe in the day time: and that Piller of fire, which neuer left the face of Gods choſen in the night.</p>
            <p>Not vnlike to this was that Blazing ſtarre (as I ſuppoſe) which threatning deſtruction to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> was of no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance then terrour, enduring the ſpace of a whole yeare, which is not proper to naturall Blazing ſtars.</p>
            <p>To conclude, as well Diuines as Philoſophers and Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers affirme thus much in this caſe, that alwayes, in a maner, <hi>Blazing ſtars</hi> doe ariſe of caſes naturall, albeit the Lord God is the prncipall author and worker of them, as in the Chapter following it is euident.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>Whereof Blazing ſtarres do engender; according to the rules of Philoſophers; and the Canons of Aſtronomers, and what they are in deed. CHAP. VI.</head>
            <p>COncerning <hi>Blazing ſtarres</hi> I finde ſome diſagreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Philoſophers and Aſtronomers. <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:152090:7"/>
               <hi>Democritus</hi> ſayde, <hi>That a Blazing ſtarre was nothing elſe but a certaine bright ſhining in the Element procured by the coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of two ſtarres:</hi> To which opinion, I my ſelfe of late did ſomewhat encline and leane.</p>
            <p>Otherſome alſo there were, which ſuppoſed a Blazing ſtarre to be but a certaine dimme and darke light compaſſed, and (as it were) cloſed vp in a cloud. Other ſome ſayd, that it was a cloud purged, and purified from earthly matter and groſſeneſſe, which receiuing light from the other Stars, caſteth abroad clear ſtrakes of brightneſſe, ſmal and ſlender, like vnto hayre, or fine wrought flaxe,</p>
            <p>Otherſome againe, thought a Blazing ſtarre to be but a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cloude,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle his opinion of Blazing ſtars, and their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</note> kindled and ſet on fire with a hote flaming clearnes whoſe opinion <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſéemeth to haue fauoured, who ſuppoſed that a Blazing ſtarre did conſiſt of a drye vapour, which béeing drawne vpward into the higheſt ayre, is there ſet on fire: and that this <hi>blazing ſtarre</hi> taketh ſubſtance of earthly exhalations, very hote, dry, fat and clammy: which béeing carryed into the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per region of the ayre, is there kindled and burneth: to whom all Philoſophers (in a manner) of this our age haue ſubſcribed, and ſome Aſtronomers alſo, who with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> thinke no leſſe, then a blazing ſtar to be but an earthly vapour, ſomewhat thicke, faſt and fat in ſubſtance, like oyle or birdlime which being drawne vpward, me to the Spheare of the fiery Element, and touching the hollownes of the Orbe or circle, is therby heat rarified, made thin and ſet in a flame: ſo that by the conſent and mutuall agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe two ſects (although ſome doe vary) it is concluded that a Blazing ſtar is engendred and made of Ayre, ſet on fire, by reaſon of the neereneſſe of the Element of Fire, that Ayre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth in the matter and ſtuffe of a <hi>blazing ſtarre,</hi> and that the Ayre next adioyning, and being by the element of fire, is called a Blazing ſtarre, and is no leſſe indeed then it is named. Which repreſenteth the colour of fire to our eyes, becauſe the drie vapour in it is kindled, burneth, and laſteth with the light of the flame, which is moued to and fro, by the vnder ayre: where vapours of like nature, quality and ſubſtance ariſing, giue continuance and length thereunto, whereby it purchaſeth the name, after which it is vſually called.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:7"/>Vpon this agrée our late Phyloſophers, in a manner all, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the doctrine of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> worthy credite and ſubſcription: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as well the ſect <hi>Stoicall</hi> vary therefro,<note place="margin">The opinion of the Stoicks touching Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtarres.</note> affirming <hi>Blazing ſtarres</hi> to be but ordinarie Starres, not differing from other Starres which appeare in the Ayre, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee aboue thirty and two in number, not as alſo they, which hold this for a veritie, <hi>blazing Starres</hi> to be perpetuall Starres, and to kéepe a limited courſe or compaſſe, but neuer to blaze and gliſter in the Ayre: ſaue when they are left and forſaken of the Sunne, whoſe cleareneſſe dimmeth and dampeth vp their brightneſſe, that it can neither ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare nor be perceiued. And they in like ſort, which leane to this opinion, that <hi>blazing ſtarres,</hi> be Starres, hauing their certaine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted times of appearance.</p>
            <p>Now, as I diſſent not from the firſt, thoſe I meane, whoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion draweth néereſt to reaſon and trueth, ſo I varie not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from them, who hold opinion that a <hi>blazing ſtarre</hi> may bée ſupernaturall, and alſo naturall, and that the ſame taketh gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a fat human, and of fiery force, whereby it is diſſolued, and at the length conſumeth.</p>
            <p>Whereupon this conſequent is to be inferred, that we cannot call a <hi>Blazing Starre</hi> properly a Starre, but <hi>Catachreſtically,</hi> as we may ſo terme them, I meane (vſing in our phraſe of ſpéech) a certaine abuſe: although <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> (whereof we haue giuen a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the beginning of this our Treatiſe) called that Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Starre, which appeared at ſuch a time as he publiſhed his Pageants of Triumph, by the name of a Star: and which vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped name alſo <hi>Suctonius</hi> applyeth to the ſelf ſame thing: they both adding vnto it this word <hi>Crinitus,</hi> which we alſo, with no leſſe abuſe then they call Blazing.</p>
            <p>This Blazing Starre aforeſayd, which appeared in the time of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> and ſhined ſo gloriouſly, ſome imagine,<note place="margin">An erronious opinion miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueds</note> and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to be the ſelfe ſame ſtarre which directed the Wiſemen to the place where Chriſt was borne. But I cannot allow of this opinion, and why I do ſo much miſlike thereof, the reaſons in the next Chapter following, do declare. In the meane ſeaſon, I would not wade into wonders aboue my capacitie, leſt I wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in wilderneſſes of doubts, but I deſire rather to be wiſe with ſoberneſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:8"/>
            <head>Whether the ſtarre which conducted the Wiſemen to the place where Chriſt was borne, were the Blazing ſtarre, whereof the Emperour Auguſtus did ſpeake, calling it by the name of a ſtarre. CHAP. VII.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian duty admoniſheth me, in few words to make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, what maner of miraculous and ſtrange Starre that was, which (after a rare and wonderfull faſhion) lead the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vnto Chriſt being in his infancie. Which ſame men (verie raſhly, and with want of aduiſement) coniecture to be the <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtarre,</hi> which appeared, and caſt a great light at the ſame time, that <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> made ſhew as of great pampe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie, whoſe ariſing was in the North part of heauen, about the eleuenth houre of the day, and continued (as <hi>Plinie</hi> playnely teſtifieth) ſeuen dayes ſpace full and complete.</p>
            <p>Of which thing, although <hi>Picus Mirandula</hi> hath not godly and grauely diſcourſed: yet thinke I, that it is my duety, compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly to reaſon, what in this point may be mainteined, without hurt or preiudice. And ſo much the rather, becauſe I would not ſeeme in this matter, to fauour the Aſtrologians, for ſo much as they ſwarne as farre from trueth, as the world is made, and the heauen is high.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Starre, I mean that which appeared at Chriſt his natiuity, the Euangeliſt, whoſe euidence is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yed with the touchſtone of trueth, writeth in this wiſe. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> garten Aſtera auton en <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e anatole.</hi>
               <note place="margin">For we haue ſeene his ſtarre in the Eaſt.</note> Among all which word of this clauſe, penned, by the finger of the Euangeliſt, the Latine interpreter turneth this word <hi>con Aſtera, <hi>Scotland</hi>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (no doubt) and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> The Euangeliſt yet againe ſaith thus <hi>And behold, the ſtarre which they ſaw in the Eaſt, went before them, vntill by approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it ſtood ouer the place, where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:8"/>By theſe teſtimonies, it is apparant and manifeſt, that neither <hi>After,</hi> nor <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ion,</hi> doe ſignifie <hi>Blazing ſtarre.</hi> Whereby the errours of <hi>Phlenon</hi> and <hi>Harpocrates,</hi> are conuinced,<note place="margin">They appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry regions &amp; at ſundry times of great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: ergo they were dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſtarres.</note> who alſo déemed that the Starre which ſhewed and ſhined in the Eaſt, and was the Wilemens direction to <hi>Iudaea,</hi> was the ſelfſame <hi>Blazing Starre,</hi> which in the time of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> (as is aforeſayde,) ſo gloriouſly gliſtered: when it is as euident (as the Sunneſhine at nooneday) how that <hi>Blazing-Starre</hi> appeared many yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Natiuitie of Chriſt, and aroſe in the North part of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: whereas the Starre (which was the wiſemens guide into <hi>Bethlehem</hi> (appeared in the Eaſt.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, what man would ſo ſeene be allured to belieue that a <hi>Blazing Starre</hi> would be thought of the Wiſe men, a thing of ſuch certaine and infallible Prognoſtication, that the ariſing and procéeding thereof, ſhould embolden them to commence ſuch tedious iourneyes, and to attempt ſo many weary labors: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they might bee of this opinion and iudgement as well, that the <hi>Blazing ſtarre</hi> gaue foreknowledge of ſomething elſe, beſides the Natiuitie and byrth of the King of the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore it is more credible, that thoſe Wiſe men followed the Starre which then appeared, eyther vppon perſwaſion of the booke which <hi>Seth</hi> compiled: or elſe by the motion of <hi>Balaams</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie: for that they were of the Kindred and affinitie of him, as ſome hold opinion: Or elſe by the miniſtery of Angels, or by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly inſpiration, or elſe by admonition &amp; warning giuen in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, which might (why not?) giue them vnderſtanding as wel of this, as it gaue them knowledge (afterwards) to auoyd the preſence of <hi>Hreod,</hi> and to returne another way into their countrey, and not the ſame by which they came.</p>
            <p>No man is able ſufficiently to declare the enenicus opinion of <hi>Iulianus,</hi> that irreligious reuolter,<note place="margin">Iulianus the Apoſtata his opinion, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to reaſon &amp; veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie refuted.</note> who affirmeth this Starre (which hée calleth by the name of <hi>Aſaph,</hi> according to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Aegyptians</hi>) of cuſtome and went, to appeare euery foure hundreth yeares, and that it betokeneth many things both maruellous and mortall.</p>
            <p>But tell me (if thou canſt) thou falſe Prophet and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe Apoſtata, if thou wilt haue thine opinion, carry away,
<pb facs="tcp:152090:9"/>
countenance of credite: How commeth it to paſſe, that thoſe Wiſemen neuer attained to the vnderſtanding of that Starre, and the determinate ariſing of the ſame,<note place="margin">A queſtion to good purpoſe.</note> at a definite and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, but that they then came to the intelligence therof, when it was within the contemplation and view of their eyes? How commeth it to paſſe that the appearance thereof was ſo far from horror and mortalitie, and that it gaue preſignification of ioy, that to them was borne the King of the Iewes? And if it be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall to worke wonders, and to compaſſe ſtrange and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous euents, why then did it not euery foure hundred yeares (by ſucceſſion, ſeaſon and degrees of times) prognoſticate ſome ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blable thing, like vnto that which was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated to the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of the Wiſemen? why did it not, after a thouſand, fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirty yeares, or within the compaſſe and reuolution of that time, bring forth a new King to the world, or ſom other rare and wonderfull effect, to kindle in the hearts of men, manifeſt admiration? or elſe if it ſuffered an Eclipſe or depriuation of that ſingular qualitie, and ſo become drye, barren, and vnfruitfull: why did it not appeare ſtill, though weakened in working, but leſt vtterly and for euer appearance in the Heauens.</p>
            <p>Thou ſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueſt therefore, and wandreſt farre and wide from the ſincere truth, and giueſt a witneſſe of thy pertinacy to all people, and of thy ſoule impiety towards God, in that thine owne opinion, which is meere erronious, ſeemeth vnto thée paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing plauſible: thou (in the meane ſeaſon) derogating from chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religions due reuerence, and ſtrugling with tooth &amp; nayle to make it contemptible. But all in vaine, thou wreſtles with the waues, which in the end will ouerwhelme thee in thy wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. For, the truth giueth in a contrary verdict againſt thee, with the which whoſoeuer haue armed themſelues to encounter ſucceſſe hath not beene proſperous, becauſe they attempted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with a mightier then themſelues, and béeing ouermatched, were carried into captiuity,<note place="margin">The Authors iudgement in the winding vp of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie.</note> and caſt into confuſion. This Starre therefore which the Wiſemen ſaw, was no <hi>Comet</hi> or <hi>Blazing-Star,</hi> as diuers haue dreamed, but ſom new ſtar which of purpoſe was appointed to expreſſe the prouidence of God, as in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell it is apparant: not being of the number &amp; hoſt of them, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God garniſhed the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the creation: but differing
<pb facs="tcp:152090:9"/>
all Starres both Fixed, Wandering and Blazing, which to bee this teſtimonie affoordeth authoritie; For that there bee ſome which are of this iudgement, and holds it for a veritie: <hi>That in this ſtare (as in a glaſſe) was included the likenes of a Childe:</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which Opinion they might (peraduenture) be induced, by the words of the Wiſe-men ſaying: <hi>Beholde, wee haue ſeene his ſtarre in the Eaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It could not chooſe then, but be a newe Starre, and a Starre importing a myracle: For ſo much as neyther the ſelfe ſame, nor any like vnto it, euer appeared in the former ages, nor at any time ſhined in the skies for the ſpace of a thouſand fiue hundred and thirty years, after the Natiuity of our comfortable Sauior, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I ſay, a ſtarre by the grace of God created, for the execution of his meſſage, whoſe pleaſure being accompliſhed it conſumed, vaniſhed, and was no longer obiect to the eye-fight of men being cauſall and temporall, not naturall and continuall.</p>
            <p>But of this Diſcourſe ſufficient is ſayde, as well for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing of vnſauoury opinions, as alſo for the diſcouering of the infallible truth requirable in this preſent purpoſe. Now will I make a retrogradation, and returne to mine arguments, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Comets or Blazing ſtars, hauing thought my pen not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfully occupyed in this laſt particular.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>Whether Blazing ſtarres proport and foreſhew ſome ſtrange &amp; wonderfull thing to follow. CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <p>IT is called in controuerſie, whether <hi>Cometes</hi> commonly ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Blazing-ſtarres</hi> proport any prodigious thing and worlds wonder. Some in this behalfe ſeeme to bee reſolued,<note place="margin">Blazing ſtars are ſignes of ſome ſtrange thing to come</note> and make their anſwere in this ſort: That as Blazing ſtarres are rare &amp; ſeldome. ſo they ſignifie ſome thing that is rare and very ſtrange, vnto which opinion they cleaue, being thereunto drawn partly by dayly experience, and partly alſo lead by the cauſes from the which they ſet their originall.</p>
            <p>And to ſay the plaine truth, when haue Blazing ſtars caſt their glimmering beames, and lightned the ayre with their gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering brightneſſe: but ſomething hath followed, contrary to
<pb facs="tcp:152090:10"/>
common courſe, and farre otherwiſe then by vſuall and accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med order is receyued? Why then ſhould not Blazing ſtars as they are rare, ſo inferre and draw with them rare effects? And why ſhould we otherwiſe thinke, then that by their generation alſo, ſome ſtrange thing is ſignified: ſéeing that other Starres ſhining in the firmament, are thought not onely to haue béene created for the ſeruice of men: but alſo for the diſtinguiſhing of times and ſeaſons, of dayes, monethes and yeares, and for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ends alſo, which are priuy onely to Gods ſecret counſell? ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for that our Lord Ieſus, iudged not the ſuperſtitious Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes (notwithſtanding his ſore denuntiations of woes againſt them) altogether deſeruing reprehenſion: nor vtterly blamed the Sadduces for their diligent obſeruation of the Weather,<note place="margin">The Phariſies &amp; Saduces not altogether con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned for their due and preciſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the weather.</note> &amp; marking the face of the Firmament giuing iudgement: that if the coulles of Heauen were ſuch and ſuch, then ſemblable to bee the ſucces of the ſeaſons, As, if it were couered with red clouds in the euening, that then men ſhould be in expectation of the next dayes bright clearenes. Which ceremony of theirs purchaſed in proceſſe of time ſuch credite and beleefe, that it grew into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and familiar Prouerbe:
<q>
                  <l>What man can ſay of certainety.</l>
                  <l>The Euening this doth ſignifie.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX. The good and euill which Blazing ſtars doe prognoſticate, and betoken.</head>
            <p>AS it is receyued for an vndoubted truth, that <hi>Comets</hi> carry with them a Prognoſtication of ſome ſtrange wonder: ſo on the other ſide, it hath beene preciſely noted, and by due obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation confirmed, that they threaten ſome eminent euill &amp; miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe: for which conſideration a Blazing ſtarre was called, a ſigne of Heauen, A Token of great feare, by which name ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men, Authors (I meane) or Writers of ſingular lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and iudgement haue tearmed it. Not that the Blazing ſtar is to be feared, as if it could doe harme vnto man, but becauſe the omnipotent God, and guide of the heauenly hoaſt, by the ſame (as by a burning beaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) giueth vs warnings &amp; watchwords
<pb facs="tcp:152090:10"/>
of afterclaps and puniſhments: and to aſſure vs, that he it is, and none beſides him, that is vniuerſally to be feared, not with a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile, but with a filiall feare. Conſidering, that he hath peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory power ouer the whole man, body and ſoule, vpon which parts he conſiſteth: and is of ability to iudge vs to temporall chaſticement for our amendment, or elſe to condemne vs to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſtruction, as inſtruments of reprobation.</p>
            <p>But to returns to the Prognoſtrations of Comets or Blazing Stars, it is found by authority, that in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour, ſurnamed, the <hi>Great,</hi> a Blazing Starre appeared, in the contemplation whereof, the Emperour hauing his eyes earneſtly bent, and conſidering profoundly thereupon, at length he was rapt into a great aſtoniſhment, touching the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the ſame. And ſending for a Phyloſopher, named <hi>Eginard;</hi> conferred and reaſoned to and for with him about this Starre, ſaying in concluſion, that the appearing thereof did threaten vnto him ſome miſerable calamity. Which the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher hearing, to the entent that the Emperour ſhould not be more amazed then néede required, hee rehearſed the ſaying of the Prophet in theſe words: <hi>A Signis coelum nolate metuere, <hi>Feare yee not the ſignes of Heauen, and let not the viſions of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtrike terrors into your hearts.</hi>
               </hi> Which ſentence the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour not miſtiking, gaue him thanks for that comfortable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, ſaying: That he remembred the duety of a Chriſtian man to bée this namely, to ſtand in feare of nothing, but onely of him, who both created vs, and alſo this Starre. Which notable ſpéech of ſo famous an Emperour, giueth a ſenſible inſtruction, why a Blazing ſtarre may be called a token of terrour or a ſigne of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible feare. <hi>Plinie</hi> alſo (many yeers paſt) affirmed, a Comet to bee a terrible Starre, and ſo inclined to deſtruction, that it deſerued to be called mortall: as in the ciuill commotion, which was in the time of <hi>Octauius</hi> his Conſulſhip,<note place="margin">A blazing ſtar threatneth deſtruction.</note> and alſo in the warres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Pompeius</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> many probabilities are to bée ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, or rather, many verities to bee auouched. To the words of which, <hi>Plinie, Virgill</hi> (the Prince of all Poets and <hi>Plinies</hi> Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor) alludeth in this wiſe:
<q>
                  <l>More flaſhing flames of lightnings cleare.</l>
                  <l>From cloudes ſhine not below:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152090:11"/>Nor Blazing ſtars, whoſe burning beames,</l>
                  <l>Some fatall fall doth ſhew, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame Poet in another place, inſerteth theſe wordes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Strange ſtarres did ſhine from skies in darkeſome night,</l>
               <l>And flakes of fire did fill the Ayre with light:</l>
               <l>A Blazing ſtarre with ſiluered ſtrakes did ſhine,</l>
               <l>And made mens hearts for feare away to pine.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Whom the Poet <hi>Lucane</hi> imitating, and ſetting before him, as a preſident, for the obſeruation of order, vſeth theſe tearms and Phraſes of ſpéech in his Poems.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Not Blazing ſtarre with glimmering ſtrakes of light,</l>
               <l>And lengthned haires of colour red and white,</l>
               <l>Which brings to men (as many make report)</l>
               <l>Deſtruction dire in lamentable ſort.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Whereby it is to be gathered, that thoſe kinde of Writers were not ignorant, that a Comet or Blazing Starre, did moſt commonly preſignifie and foreſhew ſome imminent miſchiefe, which in tract of time came to paſſe, and thereupon grew in vſe to be called, <hi>A terrible or fearefull ſtarre.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>The miſchiefes which Blazing ſtarres forewarne to enſue. CHAP. X.</head>
            <p>FOrſomuch as it is declared already, that Blazing Starres al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſignifie nothing elſe, then the approaching of ſome pernitious and miſchieuous thing, likely after to enſue: it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth, that this queſtion be demaunded. What manner of euils they be, where Blazing Starres are premonſtrations, and foretokens? Whereunto I make this anſwere: That as Blazing Starres are diuers, ſo are their effect and euils which they ſignifie not all one, but ſundry and differing. And forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the variety or diuerſitie of them is to bée conſidered: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſary, that the effects which follow ſuch cauſes, bée
<pb facs="tcp:152090:11"/>
accordingly coniectured.</p>
            <p>Some holde opinion, that it is to be marked, which way Blazing ſtarres ſhoote their light,<note place="margin">The obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation vſed of ſome at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of Blazing ſtars.</note> becauſe (ſay they) that part of the earth ſeemeth to bee threatned, towardes which the Comet caſteth his beames thickeſt and moſt directly. Againe, it is to be noted, from what ſtarre they receyue theyr force, and whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth their influence, what things they reſemble, and repreſent in likenes, and in what places they appeare.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, to touch the effects of <hi>Blazing ſtarres,</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences manifold and innumerable haue ſealed this for a trueth,<note place="margin">The effects which haue followed Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtars proued true by experience.</note> that ſometimes they ſignifie barrenneſſe of the earth, ſometimes the ſickneſſe of the plague and peſtilence, ſomtimes dearth, and ſcarſitie of victuals, ſometimes great windes and tempeſts, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times extreame heate, ſometimes Earthquakes, ſometimes the flowing of waters beyond their bounds and banks, to the drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and loſſe of the land, ſometimes ſeditions, inſurrections, cruell commotions, tumults and battels, ſometimes chaunge of Kings and Kingdoms, alterations of common wealthes, and ſuch ſlaughters as ſeldome are ſéene: with many more cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities infinite and innumerable: inſomuch that <hi>Lucane</hi> the Poet thought it no matter of doubt, but of aſſured certainety, to call a <hi>Blazing ſtarre,</hi> ſuch a Starre as changed the ſtate of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, and wrought the alteration of principalities. His ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes follow in this order.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Strange Starres were ſeene in darkeſome nights,</l>
               <l>The Heauen was on a flame:</l>
               <l>And flakes of fire like burning brands,</l>
               <l>Sore ſights in skies did frame.</l>
               <l>The fearefull Starre which blazeth bright,</l>
               <l>And ſpreades his beames abroad,</l>
               <l>And changeth Kingdomes in the World,</l>
               <l>In th'ayre aboue abode.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:12"/>
            <head>Sundry examples and teſtimonies, declaring the diuers and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold miſchiefes, which haue followed the appearing of Blazing ſtarres. CHAP. XI,</head>
            <p>LEaſt any man ſhould thinke this méere fabulous, and a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forgery, becauſe I haue ſayde thus much, and that vyon the opinion and authority of other Writers, that diuers Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtars preſignifie and giue a forewarning of diuers miſchiefs and euils like to come, it ſeemeth vnto me an enterpriſe worth my labour, to ſet downe in a few words, and the ſelfe ſame agréeing with the true reports of Hiſtories, the aſſertion aboue mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not to be imaginacions or faigned. Wherein it ſhall not ſéeme a matter depending vpon neceſſity, to runne through all particular examples, and to make an vniuerſall repetition of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies from the Worlds Creation, (which paſſeth the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of my wit to comprehend, becauſe they excéede in multitude) But it ſhall rather be ſufficient, and much more profitable, out of many to gather a fewe, and ſuch indeede, as Authors (moſt worthy of credite) haue ſet downe in their Works and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizes.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all to beginne with the nobleſt Writers, and beſt approued:<note place="margin">A ſhort enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration or rehearſall of miſchiefes which followed vpon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtarres.</note> Who is ignorant, that after the appearance of a Comet in the time of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> not onely ciuill warres fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, in manner moſt lamentable, but alſo the death and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> his owne perſon, which was moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable? who being 56. yeares of age, was aſſalted, and ſet vpon in a conſpiracie. of 60. Princes and more, among whome were <hi>C. Caſſius, Marcus,</hi> and <hi>D. Brutus,</hi> and being gored through and flaſht with 23. wounds, in the Court of <hi>Pompeius</hi> deſpitefully periſhed, whereof <hi>P. Virgilius, Lucanus Plinie, Suetonius, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pianus, Plutarchus,</hi> and diuers other Writers of great authority are witneſſes.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I linger long in the repetition of thoſe ſtrange tempeſts, of ſnowes, haples, inundations of waters, and other like calamities, that followed the appearing of the ſame Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb facs="tcp:152090:12"/>
Starre: Which <hi>F. Horatius</hi> doth not nakedly deſcribe, but ſingularly ſet downe with a kinde complaynt.</p>
            <p>Who knoweth not, what an vnſpeakeable deſolation, and wonderful ouerthrow of <hi>Hieruſalems</hi> City, followed after the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of a certaine Blazing Star, which was ſéene in the ayre, (<hi>Ioſephus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> faithfully affirming no leſſe) by the ſpace of a whole yeare, burning with flames of lamentable deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <p>The ſelfe ſame miſerable maſſacre and deſolation followed ſhortly after this <hi>Blazing Starre,</hi> which the Lord himſelfe, the Father of all mercy, and Iudge of all reuengement, did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foretell many yeares, ere it came to paſſe: but alſo wept for very ſorrow of heart, as he was propheſying to Ieruſalem, her ſharpe Viſitation. For our Sauiour Chriſt (as the Euangeliſts teſtifie) beholding the City, wept ouer her, and ſounded as it were, in her eares this ſorrowfall ſentence: <hi>If thou haddeſt known</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in that thy day, thoſe things which belonged to thy peace, and now are hidden from thine eyes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did not the death of that moſt godly and religious Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> follow and iſſue the appearing of a <hi>Blazing Starre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Blazing ſtarre appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before the Emperour Conſtantine.</note> which was ſéene <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 304. being of an vnaccuſtomed big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; of no leſſe horror to behold? And did not therupon likewiſe follow an excéeding dangerous inſurrection in the Empire, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (among many murthers) the Emperor <hi>Conſtantius</hi> was ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of his life in the Caſtle of <hi>Helena.</hi> not farre from <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 444. a <hi>Blazing ſtarre</hi> was ſéene, which as it gaue prefigurations &amp; foretokens of afterclaps, ſo did there enſue moſt miſerable ſlauters &amp; calamityes, ſpecially in <hi>France,</hi> and not long after <hi>Collen</hi> (being aſſalted &amp; beſieged of the <hi>Hunnes</hi>) was ranſackt, ſpoiled, and made euen in a maner with the ground: and the moſt Catholicke Emperour <hi>Martian,</hi> was in a conſpiracy of his own ſubiects (contrary to the religious oath of alleagiaunce) murthered and made away at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the appearing of a Starre, in the yeare of our Lord, 584 there followed ſuch an inundation of waters, in euery place of the land, that it was auerred and beléeued, a ſecond deluge or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall floud, to haue béene prepared for the drowning of the whole World. After that enſued in <hi>Italie,</hi> ſo hote a peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb facs="tcp:152090:13"/>
that within the compaſſe of a little time, many thouſands dyed in manner moſt lamentable. Not long after that, <hi>Rome</hi> taſted of the whippe:<note place="margin">A maruellous inundation of waters, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notable calamities for warned by a Blazing ſtarre.</note> for the <hi>Lombards</hi> laying ſiege againſt it, made hauocke thereof out of meaſure. Vpon the tayle of which ſharpe puniſhment, there followed a worſe: for the <hi>Sarazens</hi> roſe vp with ſterne lookes and bending browes, compelling the third part (almoſt) of the World which profeſſed Chriſtianity, to fall to Apoſtaſie, and to take part with them in their damnable ſect of diueliſh Idolatry, and deteſtable vngodlineſſe.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lord eight hundred and thirtéene, there was a <hi>Blazing ſtar</hi> ſéene moſt ſtrange and terrible, whereupon inſued the death of that moſt Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Carolus Magnus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Blazing ſtar appeared before the death of Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Magnus.</note> The <hi>Sarazens</hi> aſſaulted <hi>Italy,</hi> and with violence of ſword and warlike Engines, ouercame and preuayled: not without the ruine of many a beautifull building, and ſhedding of much bloud.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lord, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>84. there appeared a <hi>Blazing ſtarre,</hi> which did portend a manifeſt ſhew of much miſchiefe and miſery:<note place="margin">Bloudy bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels which fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after the appearing of a Blazing flame.</note> for in the yeare of our Lord, 1302. next enſuing, that memorable and bloudy battell of <hi>Flanders</hi> was fought, which to the Frenchmen principally miniſtred occaſion of many a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Alas: for in that battell, the floure of the <hi>French</hi> Armie, I meane the chiefeſt in place and countenance, and the gemme of all their glory, went to wracke, ſuffering death no leſſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniouſly then tyrannically. And after that, <hi>Rodulph</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, making ſiege againſt <hi>Verona,</hi> ſuſtained great loſſe of his beſt appointed Souldiers, the Switzers, whoſe bloud embrued the blades of their enemies, their bodyes lying vpon the ground groueling and ſenſeleſſe: and the Emperour himſelfe fighting againſt <hi>Albert</hi> D. of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> was flain, only Emperour elected but not crowned. Now, what manifolde miſeries and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes,<note place="margin">A Blazing ſtar ſhooting vpwards, what afterwards enſued.</note> a Blazing ſtarre which ſhooteth vpward, the head hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downeward, doth betoken, may ſoone be perceyued, &amp; known by the experience of a Blazing ſtarre, which appeared in the Weſt, and tooke his courſe towards the North, which Starre was ſéene in the yeare of our Lord, 1363. The woes whereof this Starre gaue foreknowledge, fell vpon the Frenchmen, to their no ſmallſmart, and lamentable vnlukineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:13"/>For in a foughten field againſt the Turkes, howbeit, out of the compaſſe of the French dominion, they were diſcomfited and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne, a hundred thouſand of them ſlaine with the ſword, among which number was the Duke of Burgundy, who with the reſt, loſt his life without recouery.</p>
            <p>Not long after which infortunate conflict, namely, in the yeare of our Lord, 1406. <hi>Lodouicke</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> and brother to the <hi>French King,</hi> was murthered at <hi>Paris</hi> moſt trayterouſly, and frandulently: the loſſe of whoſe life was death and deſtruction to a great number.</p>
            <p>And (that I may grow to an end) who doth not remember, what grieuous calamities did follow the appearing of a <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtarre,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord, a thouſand foure hundred threeſcore and twelue, in the Moneth of Ianuary, ouer <hi>Colen</hi> Eaſtward, to the terrour of the Beholders, and aſtoniſhment of the bearers? There followed hereupon, in the Summer next, and immediately enſuing, a maruellous heate, engendred euery where in the earth, which was of ſuch ſtrength and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, that in ſome places, the firſt burſt out, and caſt vp with it, euen the very ſand and grauell. Hereupon followed, not here and there, but euery where battels and murthers, mortall maladies, loathſome ſickneſſes, moſt noyſome and infectious: yea, ſo horrible, that I want witte, eyther in writing to leaue them witneſſed or by vtterance to make them manifeſt. At which time alſo, the right renowmed <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> paſſed many warrelike aduentures, and atchieued many a Martiall exployte, to his no ſmall commendation, and encreaſe of deſerued prayſe, notwithſtanding the ſucceſſe of battel is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and dangerous.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lord, 1408.<note place="margin">Further miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes which haue followed after Blazing ſtarres.</note> there appeared a <hi>Blazing ſtarre,</hi> which as in fight it was wonderfull and terrible, ſo it betokened miſchiefe no leſſe innumerable, then either to heare, ſée, or recount is moſt lamentable: For not many dayes after, <hi>Luycke</hi> fell, and certayne men to the number of 40. were cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly flaine. About that time alſo, (the <hi>Pruſſians</hi> entring battell againſt the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> were foyled, &amp; a ſlaughter, the like not heard of) made of them in the conflict. At the ſame time alſo, was the Councel at <hi>Piſa</hi> diſſolued by a ſchiſme moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:14"/>
their conuocation and méeting, being for the making and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of vnitie.</p>
            <p>Thereabout alſo began the Church to be yll appayde, and ſo ſtand in hazard of hauocke: whoſe preſent aſſiſtent <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> ſhewed himſelfe to be, in ſuch ſort with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liancie of ſpirit, that he might meritoriouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>halenge to be ſirna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>The moſt Chriſtian King.</hi> Thus farre touching the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, yea the heapes of euils which <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> haue protended obſerued by experience and tryall to be true, by the euent &amp; falling out of many miſfortunes,<note place="margin">The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Chapter.</note> which both long agoe, and alſo of late haue happened. It remaineth that we know, whether they bée not foretokens alſo of ſome good, which although many vtterly deny, yet neuertheleſſe reade our further iudgement.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>Whether Blazing Starres, doe not as well betoken good, as ill. CHAP. XII.</head>
            <p>HAuing before declared, by reaſons not a few, and proued alſo by examples of veritie and trueth, that <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> (for moſt part) are prefignificant ſhewes and tokens of ſome miſchiefe and euill:<note place="margin">Blazing ſtars ſupernaturall ſignes ſent from God.</note> me thinkes I heare one aſking me this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. Whether <hi>Blazing ſtarres</hi> are not tokens of good, as they are ſignes of euill? To whom I make this reſolution. Firſt, ſo farre foorth as <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> be ſupernaturall, there ſeemeth in this matter to reſt no doubt: becauſe Almighty God, in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable profunditie of his wiſedome, is wont by the appearing of Stars, to giue ſignes to his beloued ſeruants (whom no doubt he hath fore elected to ſaluation) as wel of ioyful newes as alſo of heauy tidings.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Rainbow a perpetuall aſſurance of Gods faithfull promiſe.</note>For, hath he not by the riſing of the Rainebow. in the clouds of heauen, ſealed ſecurity and want of feare to the world, from being drownd, as ſomtimes it was in the dayes of our great Ancients? Did he not by the retroceſſion and backeward going of the Sun (contrary to the order of his courſe) ſignifie vnto <hi>Ezechias,</hi> that his life ſhold be prolonged, and the number of his dayes were augmented? Did he not alſo ſignifie vnto all nations, that the
<pb facs="tcp:152090:14"/>
light was come into the World, which ſhould ſhine in darkneſſe, namely, Ieſus Chriſt to bee borne for the ſaluation of all people: which thing hée would haue teſtified by the appearing of a new Orientall Starre, viſible to the eyes of the Wiſemen, and glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly gliſtering? Euen ſo doubtleſſe, there is no cauſe, why the fight of a <hi>Blazing Starre</hi> ſhould not bréede in vs,<note place="margin">Blazing ſtars naturall may betoken ſome good.</note> as well hope of ſome good, as feare of ſome ill, according to the place and time, where &amp; when it appeareth, ſince it is ſayde, <hi>Feare not the ſignes of heauen which the Gentiles feare; becauſe the lawes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are vaine.</hi> Why then ſhould we ſtand in feare of thoſe things, which haue not in them power, eyther to do good or harm? Again ſo far forth as <hi>Blaſing Stars</hi> are naturall, it is not to be doubted, but that the appearing of them may portend, and foreſhew ſome good: which is no hard or intricate matter to declare, as well by reaſon, as alſo by example.</p>
            <p>For inſomuch as <hi>blazing-Starres</hi> are made of fiue Planets, as <hi>Abienus</hi> affirmeth, namely, of <hi>Venus, Iupiter, Mars, Saturne,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mercurie:</hi> and that thoſe <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> which are made of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> are principally the beſt and luckyeſt, it cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be, but that <hi>blazing ſtars,</hi> thoſe ſpecially which haue their influence from <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> ſhould ſometimes beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken good, and not euermore euill. An example of good credit may that <hi>Blazing ſtar</hi> be, which when it appeared, was iudged ſo happy and fortunate to the Emperour <hi>Caeſar Auguſtus,</hi> that then it was begun to be worſhipped in the Temple of <hi>Rome,</hi> and no where alſo throughout the whole world: becauſe the Emperour beginning thoſe ſhewes &amp; Pageants triumphant: was by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of that ſtar ſeuen dayes continuance in the Region of heauen, put in hope and expectation afore hand, of excéeding great felicity and happineſſe to enſue: which vndoubtedly hée obtained in ſuch ſort and manner, that none in regiment was counted happier then happy <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> as none was named better then the good <hi>Traianus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, vpon the appearing of that ſtar, there bredde in the minds of the Commonalty an opinion of great reuerence, to wit that by the <hi>blazing ſtar</hi> was ſignified, the ſoule of <hi>Caeſar.</hi> to bee receyued to immortality, and to enioy among the Gods aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of bleſſednes: then which ſignification, they beléeued no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:152090:15"/>
more ioyfull or comfortable. So that we ſée both by reaſon and example, that their coniecture and opinion doth not alwayes deſerue beléefe, which ſay: that <hi>blazing Starres</hi> neuer appeare, but thereafter followeth ſome miſchiefe and ill. Touching which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more might be ſayd to the increaſe of comfort, and the driuing away of deſpayre from the hearts of the people, then we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed at this time to call to memory.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>To what Countries, and to what perſons blazing ſtarres doe principally betoken ill. CHAP. XIII.</head>
            <p>THe queſtion is aſked, To what Countries, and to what peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpecially, <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> threaten miſchiefe. Vnto which demand doubtleſſe, I might think no certain anſwer can be made: becauſe all <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> are not alike, neyther haue their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from one and the ſelfe ſame cauſe: but ſome of them are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, other ſupernaturall, and procéeding from God in the height of the heauens.</p>
            <p>Againe, they are without difference, ſo doubtfull in their ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, that <hi>Lucanus</hi> ſuppoſeth their influence to be ſo general, that the beholders of them, eyther on Sea or Land, cannot aſſure themſelues of ſafety: and therefore they are vniverſally to bée feared.<note place="margin">Blazing ſtars are vniuerſally to bee feared both on ſea and land.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Vnto whoſe opinion I willingly aſſent, when <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> (ſupernaturall, and procéeding from God) do appeare. For this is of a certainty, that it is Gods wil, by them to betoken and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſome yll, to all perſons in generall, which hauing offended and done wickedly againſt the preſcript of his holy Law; withdraw not themſelues from that puddie of pollution and filthines, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they wallow: but continue a life laden and ouercharged with al manner of miſchiefe: whom he of his ſingular compaſſion and clemencie, would reuoke from their ſinfulneſſe, by the viſion and ſight of <hi>blazing ſtarres,</hi> as it were by horrible threatnings and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokements, that by reforming their abominable liues, they might frame their conuerſation acceptable in his ſight, according to his vnſpeakeable bountifulneſſe, long ſuffering, and patience, who ſtill looketh for repentance before he taketh vengeance. As may manifeſtly be gathered, by his dealing with the <hi>Hieroſolimites,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:15"/>
whom he admoniſheth of their wickedneſſe, by a moſt horrible <hi>Blazing Starre,</hi> of a whole yeares appearing, dayly looking when they would be warued, and well appoynted with pretence, to preuent Gods ſharpe puniſhment.</p>
            <p>But touching naturall <hi>Blaſing Stars,</hi> Phyloſophers and Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomers haue otherwiſe iudged, howbeit,<note place="margin">Blazing ſtarres nataurall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare at Gods appointment.</note> neither they ſhall at any time arpeare without the ſingular ſufferance of God, or ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cauſe worthy remembrance. For my ſelfe, thus I ſay, that as I am not of beléefe, that they betoken and proue in working as the Aſtrologians dreame: So I do not vtterly condemne ſuch as hold it much materiall, &amp; greatly to be regarded: toward what part of the world they ſhoot and caſt their beams, from what ſtars they draw their influencies and force: in what ſimilitude and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they appeare, what colour they carry, at what ſeaſon of the yeare they ſhow, in what place, vnder what eccleſtiall ſignes, and vnder what Planets aſpect. For ſome there are, which hold this opinion (though grounded vpon no kind of reaſon) that a <hi>blazing ſtarre,</hi> bearing the likeneſſe of a Lute, Harpe, or ſemblable inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, betokeneth ſomewhat to Muſicks and Minſtrelſie, and to the followers of ſuch vanities. So likewiſe when they carry this repreſentation or that, to haue in their likeneſſes ſemblant ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications.</p>
            <p>Againe, other are of this iudgement, that ſuch <hi>Blazing-Starres</hi> as appeare vnder <hi>Saturne,</hi> are of a leaden colour:<note place="margin">The colour of Blazing ſtarrs appearing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Planets.</note> vnder <hi>Iupiter</hi> white: vnder <hi>Mars,</hi> red: vnder <hi>Sol,</hi> Golden: vnder <hi>Mercurie,</hi> light azur: whereupon it is thought no hard matter, to tell what they ſignifie in nature generally. Howbeit, to perſons placed in digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as to Popes, Cardinals, Biſhops, Emperors, Kigns, Lukes and ſuch like as are of place and countenance in the Common-wealth, they foreſhew ſome euill: wherein as I hold it reuerence to be ſilent: ſo were it ouermuch boldnes and preſumption to be medling. What therefore may be ſayd in this point, let Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers ſhew their cunning.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>How and what way Blazing ſtarres are forewarning of ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to come, and of force ſo to doe. CHAP. XIV.</head>
            <p>ALthough it may ſéeme diuerſely and many wayes probable, that <hi>blazing-Starres</hi> foreſhew ſomewhat to inſue: yet not
<pb facs="tcp:152090:16"/>
withſtanding it is not neceſſary, that we ſhould beléeue (as the Aſtrologians raſhly hold opinion) that they can be ſignes or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of that thing, whereof they are no cauſe. For a <hi>blazing ſtar</hi> cannot be eyther the cauſe, or the effect of warre or death: albeit, it prognoſticate and foreſhew (as a ſigne from a naturall cauſe) both the one and the other.</p>
            <p>It may be (I will not deny) the cauſe after a ſort: as if that which is the cauſe of warre and peſtilence, we ſuppoſe alſo to bée the cauſe of the <hi>blazing ſtarre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Blazing ſtars are after a ſort the cauſe of warre, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. &amp;c.</note>As when aboundance of vapours are drawne vp into the aire, which being kindled and ſet on fire, there followeth and enſueth the generation of a <hi>blazing ſtarre,</hi> and infection of the aire, which breedeth plague and peſtilence, mouing mens minds to muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, through the increaſe and plenty of choller ſtirred vp in them: whereby they runne with maine force to harneſſe and weapon, and ſo to battel and bloudſhed, not féeling in them any rule of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, reſtrayning them in this their raſhnes. Hereupon (as it is not vnlike) ſpring commotions in kingdomes, and mutations of Commonwealths, then deſtructions: for, <hi>A realme diuided within it ſelf, being vnable long to laſt, muſt needs come to loſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Blazing ſtars foretokens of barrenneſſe.</note>Furthermore, ſeeing that the generation of a naturall <hi>Blazing Starre,</hi> importeth that in ſome place hath béene great heate and drought, (for otherwiſe ſuch ſtore of matter as is required to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ingendring thereof, could not be drawne vp:) it is wont to come to paſſe, that <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi> doe commonly threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten barrenneſſe to Sandie, and not to Fenny Countries.</p>
            <p>Now, becauſe it is likewiſe knowne, that by force of Starres, many enuenomed and infectious vapours aſcend,<note place="margin">Blazing ſtars foretokens of peſtilence and mortalitie.</note> it ſéemeth cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible that a <hi>blazing ſtarre</hi> is a forewarning of a following peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ingendred through the ayre, béeing choked and poyſoned by vapours of ſuch quality. By which means in like maner, drought ſetteth mens hearts on fire, and driueth them forward to fall at ſtrife, bralling, battell, and bloodſhed: it troubleth the brain, eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the ſeaſes, and thus ariſeth ſeditions. To conclude with the purpoſe, it is not greatly neceſſary in this declaration, to vſe lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger delay, ſince I am of this beléefe, that God (of the aboundance of his loue towards vs, which is vnmeaſurable) by nature, as a meane or méete inſtrument, cauſeth ſuch and ſuch <hi>blazing ſtarres</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:16"/>
to appeare: to the intent, that he might by them (as by premoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and fore warnings) put vs in mend to remember, that it is time to ſtart from ſinne, and to prepare our hearts with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for preuenting of thoſe ſharp and ſmarting whips of Gods vengeance, which by ſuch <hi>Blazing Starres,</hi> at Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are threatned. For he neuer or very ſeldome, ſince the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world plagued any people: but he ſent among them ſome ſigne thereof, for their preparation to penitence, as in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures it is at large declared.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>Why Blazing Starres do ſpecially betoken ill to Peeres, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, Rulers of Realmes and Commonwealthes, &amp;c. CHAP. XV.</head>
            <p>IT is the opinion of ſome, though erronious, that <hi>blazing ſtars</hi> do ſpecially betoken ill to Princes and great men, and to their Kingdomes alſo and Realmes threaten ſome miſchiefe: in ſuch wiſe, that it hath béene obſerued and marked, that no <hi>blazing ſtar</hi> almoſt hath appeared, but either death, or elſe ſome ill hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after, to ſome noble perſonage in the land; as by our former examples it is left verified: which made <hi>Lucan</hi> the Poet to write of them, in this wiſe:
<q>
                  <l>A Blazing Starre in ſight moſt ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>The ſtate of kingdomes, which doth change.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But it is here demanded, what the cauſe ſhould be, that Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Starres do ſpecially betoken ill to Emperours, Kings, and ſuch like noble perſonages? I anſwer, that there is none other cauſe, as they ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">Why Blazing ſtars betoken ill to Peeres and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates: &amp;c.</note> ſo farre forth as Blazing Starres be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, then becauſe ſuch great eſtates and Péeres of Realmes, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more delicately and vntemperately then other: are ſooner ſubiect and ſurpriſed with corrupt and empoyſoned ayre: and ſo they carrying cloſe within them, and ſecretly nouriſhing the cauſe of ill in themſelues, being vnpatient and not able to indure the working of medicinable receipts, quickely periſh and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:17"/>But ſo farre forth as <hi>Blazing-Starres</hi> are ſupernaturall, and as they haue their procéeding and béeing from the omnipotent God, it is thought this to be the cauſe: namely, that God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring a plague againſt them, that the blacke tents of his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation are pitching, that the weapons of his vengeance are whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt them, whereof he giueth forewarnings, like a moſt mercifull Father: to the end they might vnderſtand, that the cauſe of this Gods iuſt dealing, (being ſinne and wickednes,) is either in Princes themſelues, or elſe in the people vnder their vngratious gouernment: in conſideration whereof, as well prince as people might ſée the horrour and abhomination of their owne ſinfull liues, and flye to repentance, whereunto God ſo fatherly would win them by forewarnings.<note place="margin">The wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the people is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the prince.</note> That according to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of that holy King, they may lift vp both hearts and hands to heauen, ſaying: <hi>Enough now Lord, ſtay thy hand, It is I that haue offended: it is I that haue done wickedly: as for theſe innocent ſheepe, what harme haue they done?</hi> Furthermore, to whom doth a Blazing Star betoken ſomewhat to follow, if not to the King? For in that it ſignifieth ſomewhat to the Realme, it muſt extend euen to the perſon of the King, who hath the rule and gouernment of that Realme: becauſe he is a King by his Kingdome, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the wickednes of the kingdome, is reputed the wickedneſſe of the King, who either by his enſample giueth occaſion of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe:<note place="margin">A heauy rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning for ſuch as are in authoritie and office.</note> or elſe hauing power and authority to ſuppreſſe ſinne in the people, neglecteth notwithſtanding the due execution and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of iuſtice: ſo that the ſaying of the Apoſtle is moſt certaine and vndoubted: that, All thoſe whom God hath placed in authority, giuen preheminence vnto, are tyed to the neceſſity of this heauy reckning, not only to ſtand accountable to almighty God for their owne, but alſo for the ſoules of all ſuch ouer whom they haue charge. And therefore right aptly ſpake that moſt wiſe and worthy King <hi>Dauid</hi> to all Kings, (and vnder their title, to all ſuch as excell other in office &amp; dignitie:) <hi>And now ye kings</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vnderſtand, be ye learned which iudge the earth, ſerue the Lord with feare, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus farre touching this matter, which though it be but bluntly and and ſhortly deliuered, yet is it to be marked.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:152090:17"/>
            <head>Of a certaine Blazing ſtarre which appeared in the yeare, 1531. the 19. of Sept. at Mentz, a City in Germany, and was ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſeeene likewiſe in other places. CHAP. XVI.</head>
            <p>A Queſtion is asked, what that <hi>Blazing ſtarre</hi> which was ſeene in the yeare 1531. might ſignifie, and to whom it is a foretoken of ſome euill to enſue. In anſwering whereunto, I would to God, I might not tell the truth ſo directly, as I did of an Earthquake 3, years paſt, the effects whereof, the City of <hi>Mentz,</hi> not without trembling taſted. The Blazing ſtarre which appeared, 1531. betokens a heauie burthen of vengeance, not onely to the ſtate temporall, but alſo eccleſiaſticall: yea it threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a plague to the whole world. The faſhion and likenes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſignifieth no leſſe, for it was to ſée to, in forme of a broome, or a bundell of rods: which figure of a rod we doubt, forwarneth vs of that rod, wherof the Lord ſpeaketh by the Prophet: <hi>I will vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite their iniquities with the rod, and their ſins with ſtripes.</hi> For Almighty God vſeth for more certainety of forewarning, to giue vnto ſignes and tokens, the likeneſſes of things ſignified, and betokened. As for example.</p>
            <p>At what time his will was to forewarne the <hi>Iewes</hi> of the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian</hi> captiuity, he ſpake thus to <hi>Ieremie</hi> the Prophet: <hi>Make thee fetters and chaines, and put them about thy necke, &amp;c.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſignifie their captiuity. So the ſame God, gaue a ſign in the ayre of <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Veſpaſian;</hi> his huge hoaſt againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to lay it waſte: armed men with ſpeares and lances, running to and fro in warlike wiſe, which though they ſaw manifeſtly, yet ceaſt they not to liue as they were wont, moſt wickedly, the vengeance of God falling vpon them, which by thoſe forewarnings was propheſied.</p>
            <p>In the yeare, 1500, there was ſéene falling from heauen vpon mens garments, Croſſes, and there appeared in ſenſible manner,<note place="margin">A ſtrange ſight and wonderful forewarning of a bloudie battell.</note> as certaine ſignes what ſhould after come to paſſe: namely, that bloudy battell betwéene the two worthy Princes <hi>Rupert</hi> the 3. ſon of <hi>Philip,</hi> Palſegraue of <hi>Rhene,</hi> and Prince Elector, and the noble Prince <hi>Albert,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauaria:</hi> the enſignes of the one hauing blacke croſſes, &amp; the other red: ſo that in the yeare 1504. was fulfilled that which in the yeare 1500. was foretolde</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152090:18"/>Wherefore it is to bee feared, leſt the Blazing ſtarre which was ſéene in the likeneſſe of a rodde, threaten vnto vs that rodde which the Prophet ſpake of, wherewith God is purpoſed in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to viſite the wickedneſſe of the people. For if this Blazing ſtarre bée naturall, wée ſhall perceyue nothing in it, which betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not ſome great euill.<note place="margin">All miſchiefe commeth from the North.</note> Firſt, becauſe it blazed ſo euen from the Weſt to the North, from whence (as witneſſeth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) all miſchiefe doth procéede, hauing neuertheleſſe an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect into other quarters of the world, terrible &amp; thretning enough.</p>
            <p>It was variable in colour, ſometimetimes pale, that is, Leaden and Saturnine, ſometimes Red and Martiall. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, in ſo much as it continued (by the auerment of Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers) vnder <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> Planets and Signes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckie influence: it ſeemeth to betoken not onely vnto one, or two Countries, but to the whole World, famine, warre, and peſtilence: for it blazed moſt terribly into all parts of the world.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if the ſame <hi>Blazing ſtarre</hi> were ſupernatural, and immediate from God, contrary to the courſe and order of Nature, it might not otherwiſe be thought, but that it betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the world much miſery and woe: for God thereby ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that his vengeance was to come vpon all wicked world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and vpon all ſuch perſons, as (to their impenitence) ioyne continuance in ſinne.</p>
            <p>Now, who hath the face to ſay againſt this, that the Worlde hath taken ſuch a ſurfet in iniquitie, and is become ſo drunken in all abomination, that Gods mercy is changed into iudgement, &amp; his patience into puniſhment, his loue into wrath, and his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into fury: in ſuch wiſe that it may be ſuppoſed, God to ſpeake vnto vs by this Blazing ſtarre, as it were out of a cloude, in this manner: <hi>The end of all fleſh is before me. The whole earth is filled full of their iniquity, and I will ſweepe them away from the face of the earth, For they haue all played the ſtart backs, they haue walked in the by-wayes of wickednes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A ſuppoſed ſpeech of God expreſſing his wrath concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</note> 
               <hi>and are becom vnprofitable: inſomuch that there is none that doth good, no not one.</hi> Which as none can deny, ſo I thinke none dares but thus confeſſe, that the Blazing ſtar ſéene in our <hi>Horizon,</hi> betokeneth a common calamity, conſidering how iniquity doth abound in a places, and that ſinne is growne to a perfect maturity and ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:152090:18"/>
which God of his mercy giue vs grace to amend, that wee féele not the heate of his conſuming anger, whereof hee hath ſent vs a forewarning.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>Whether ſuch euils as Blazing ſtars betoken, may by any meanes eyther be preuented or auoyded. CHAP. XVII.</head>
            <p>IT remayneth (moſt puiſſant Emperour) the premiſſes conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that your Maieſty taking the King of <hi>Niniuie</hi> for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, riſe vp from your ſeate of Royalty, and putting on ſackcloath together with vs your people, lift vp our hands and hearts to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, praying to God moſt heartily, like humble ſuters.</p>
            <p>Now who is ſo blunt of iudgement, and dul of vnderſtanding that ſéeth not that the confeſſion of offences, the repentance and contrition of heart, the humbling and ſubmitting our ſelues both in ſoule and body vnder the mighty hand of the omnipotent God, will pacifie and aſſwage the fierceneſſe of his fury, and ſo ſpare vs in compaſſion, through vnfained repentance, that wee periſh not as outcaſts from his fauour.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould we not haue this hope and confidence in God,<note place="margin">God doth not exclude the penitent from the throne of grace, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth them to his mercy.</note> conſidering that to the penitent Niniuites he did not ſhutte the gates of his compaſſion, but ſéeing their conuerſion and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſinne, with the denyall of themſelues, and all goodnes in them, he receyued them againe to mercy, from which by their ſinnes they were before excluded.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it is not needeful that we ſtand in feare of the celeſtiall Signes, becauſe without God they haue no power at al to preuayle againſt any people; but being his ſeruants, are at his commaundement, from whom all ſtars and all creatures haue their office and miniſtery. To conceyue terror and feare therefore at the appearing of a Blazing ſtar, as betokening ſome euill like to follow, it is extreame madneſſe: let vs rather tremble at his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightines, and feare the conſuming flames of his iuſtice, who is the Creator and maker, not onely of Blazing ſtars, but alſo of the Sunne, Moone, and Planets, yea of reaſonable man.</p>
            <p>And let vs not thinke, but that God, who framed the
<pb facs="tcp:152090:19"/>
whole world, the heauen aboue, and the earth below, is able (as he made them) ſo to rule them: for at his commandement are all things within the compaſſe of the Heauen, be they Starres, or whatſoeuer elſe: ſo that he can; according to the greatneſſe of his power, which filleth all places, chaunge and diſpoſe them, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his owne pleaſure: yea the threatning tokens of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vengeance, will he turn into forbearance and forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if we penitently neglect not (as did the <hi>Iewes</hi>) the time of our Viſitation: For they being warned by many wonders, and among others, by a Blazing ſtarre, of no leſſe horrour then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance: lay ſlugging in the Couch of ſecurity and careleſneſſe, and not regarding the threats of God for ſinne, eyther of wilfull blindneſſe, or ſtout ſtubbornneſſe, counted thoſe tokens of Gods vnſufferable wrath, elementarie apparitions, and toyes méerely contemptible.</p>
            <p>But let vs not ſuffer our ſelues to bée lulled aſléepe in the cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of ſenſuality:<note place="margin">It is good to be warned by the example of others.</note> Let vs not bée drunken with the dregs of their abomination: Let not the vanities of our owne hearts ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch vs, that we fall into a ſelfe loue and liking of our owne ſelues, neglecting the preffered time of grace and louing kindnes leſt God deliuering vs ouer to reprobation in his vnappeaſeable diſpleaſure, plague vs with the ſame rod of reuengement for our vngraciouſnes, wherewith hee tooks vengeance vpon them for their wilfull ſtubborneneſſe. Which that it may not come to paſſe, let vs in time turne to the Lord, and in due ſeaſon take his fatherly admonitions, as ready meanes to lead vs to repentance and the auoyding of the ſcourge of deſtruction, wherewith he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the impenitent. From the which deliuer vs O Lord God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Almighty, Euerlaſting. Inuiſible, and onely wiſe God, bee All, aboue All, and in All, all Laude, Honour, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Dominion and Maieſty for euer and euer, Amen,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
